[Music]
before the
weekend we had the
discussion of how to move a sub manifold
an object inside the man how to move it
around and whether you run into
obstacles or you could go around
obstacles and so on we also saw that
these questions had answers in terms of
the dimensions if you are moving a small
dimensional thing in a large dimensional
ambient space it's easy to move whereas
if you had a large dimensional
relatively large dimensional Subspace
moving inside a small dimensional
ambient space it's difficult overflow
and that kind of idea
you let's begin by an example
which serves as a quick revision can you
visualize this
surface I hope you
can it's made of a
tube question in what
dimensional ambient space r m for what M
can this let's call it it tube not
because it's a not K in French which is
made of a
tube the
unoted
to an ordinary
taus a quick reminder you
remember from Friday that if you
had an ordinary not made of string so
this Cube not is made of
surface but if you have and not made of
string like this you want to unot it to
this
shape you cannot do this in R3 in our
space that's clear we cannot undu this
but we can do this if we can pass one
thing past another by going around it
and in what d dial space can you do this
and nothing it's in your notebooks huh
it's not four I think or is it four it's
four sorry in R4 you can do this so in
R3 you cannot but R4 you can I'm asking
the same question but for not made of
tues so what do you think the answer
is how high dimension do you need in the
ambient space in order to do this
huh any take
us that's very good how do you calculate
six you are genius so answer why
six y
six do you remember if you're moving
something of a certain Dimension K
dimensional thing
yeah what's the dimension of this tube
Note two
and you want to move it past itself in
other you want to move a two-dimensional
object past the two dimensional object
so K and L that I mentioned on Friday
are both this tube so two Dimension plus
two Dimension and then you calculate the
Overflow minus M which is the ambient
room available if you like and if this
is what strictly less than minus one you
succeed in doing this if it's equal
minus one you run it an obstacle but at
points and so on so that's the answer
and if you rearrange these pieces and so
on you get that M must be greater than
or equal to six so in Dimensions six and
above you can undo all tube
notes so next time you see for example
next to As in that direction and there
is a hose
with which you can squirt water in case
you come back from the beach and you're
all full of sand and if you twist it and
not it and so on well you can unot it
without cutting the tube Notting R3
Notting R4 not in R5 but if you go to
six dimensional space or higher you can
do this okay that's the kind of thing
let's systematize this
idea by
introducing a piece of
terminology imagine then in general that
we are moving one object through some
ambient space
imagine we are
[Applause]
moving at sub
manifold just think of it as a geometric
figure k um in an in an
ambient
manifold M you remember abbreviation MF
LD that stands for man fold a strange
term which just means geometric
figure and the picture we shall draw
is let's say that this is what K looks
like think of it as a string if you like
but it has any Dimension okay so that's
one good example any Dimension and I
moving it and as it
moves I'm I'm going
to finally arrive at this position so
I'm going to denote by K sub Z the
initial position and K sub one the final
position where it gets to and at
intermediate
stages at time
T I'm going to denote this object by K
subt is that clear so as time progresses
from zero to one from beginning to end
I'm moving this through space like this
like this and then like this and like
this and like this and like this and so
forth okay that's what we are doing now
um in words case of T
denotes the position of
[Applause]
K at
time T which is between Z and one Z is
the beginning t one is at the end okay
suppose that we do this a very
reasonable in fact a common sensical
supposition that you never self
intersect K okay if at no time K T never
has self
intersections at any
T in other words I'm not
cheating if you move honestly then we
say that k0 is
isotopic the initial K is isotopic to
the final K K1 so that's the word
isotopic
two and here
is a little bit of symbol we shall write
this as I'm sorry that I'm coming to the
next board k0 and K1 are not equal of
course because they are in different
positions and they're not quite the same
thing in fact they have they might have
changed shape but continuous deformation
without self intersection they of course
homeomorphic but there's more we shall
write it like this which is you can see
it's weaker than homeomorphism
homeomorphism has
two equality is straight this is we weer
and we shall say that they are opic K
inside M by the way I have to say
something else here I'm
sorry in
m and
write this so that's the notation
okay as usual in mathematics when we
Define
something we have to check our
understanding by having many examples
this is a good opportunity perhaps to
give you a little speech you know when
you learn
mathematics pure applied you learn a lot
of definitions and let's say that you
have a certain number of definitions
okay maybe you learn 100
definitions also there are number of
theorems and there number of examples to
which the theorem is apply
now a good piece of mathematics if you
are a good mathematician and you're
being intelligent if you're being
economical you should have many more
theorems than definitions and you should
have many more examples than
theorems that's a good situation
unfortunately everywhere in the
world it happens that in textbooks in
classrooms you learn 100 definitions
you have to memorize definitions 100
definitions and then you learn 10
theorems and then there's only one
example it should be the other you
should have one definition 10 and 100 or
even 10,000 examples to which the
theorem is appli so please make sure
that the inequality is are in this
direction not the other way around in
our case we shall see some examples here
immediately a surprising example
can you visualize what this
picture represents I hope you
can and I hope that by now after one
week you have got into the habit of
drawing pictures
quickly do you see what this picture
really represents
I hope you can see exactly what I'm
seeing so if you like this is a
balloon but there is an arm that comes
out of the balloon another arm and those
two arms uh have sort of circular things
to toic shapes and then they're linked
with each
other is that okay they're made of
surfaces they're not
curves okay so one sort of
balloon like thing another surface here
and they are linked like this okay is
that clear now let's consider this
surface and another surface which
is the same
surface but those two arms if you like
are unlink
[Applause]
question are these surfaces
isotopic
in R six
M you answer the question for that case
do you think these are isotopic in R
six you said that that not is isotopic
to that not in R six Six Dimensions do
you think this is isotopic to this in R
six the question is whether you can go
do go from here to
here whether a surface which has
Dimension two can go past another
surface in dimension two of Dimension
two by going around in extra Dimension
do you think six is enough yes something
yes it's exactly the same calculation so
six is enough question can you do this
isotopy in dimension
three let's take a
vote in dimension three so in our space
who thinks that it's possible to isotope
this to this or this to this in
dimension three please raise your
hands okay you do you do two people only
who thinks that oh three people okay Ser
in the corner and who thinks that they
are not isotopic in R
three you have to vote for one or the
other who's to shy to
vote
okay let's try to
isotop answer and all those Isotopes
yeah isotop excuse me are in R3 okay so
when I write this I'm not going to write
this m or R R3 every time but it means
in R three okay first please imagine
that I take this arm and then make this
hole larger and larger so what we shall
see is the following picture
maybe I'm not going to draw a face every
time okay you agree that this is a
stopic to this I it's you can do it
continuous deformation with no self
intersections inside R three you can do
this yeah I just made the hole larger
but now I'm going to position these
things a little differently
this is of course ioic
right this bottom has been expanded a
little bit continuous no self
intersection
now we
shall grab this in front and move it
around over on this side and move we
should grab this thing in the back and
move it around over in the
back I slide those handles around on the
surface okay as a result what we get is
in fact
amazingly this kind of
picture well
this thing came from behind and this
tube came from in front after I do
this okay and it's clear that I can now
deform these back to
this so the answer is
[Applause]
yes surprising h
but true i' we've proved it completely
rigorous proof because we showed every
step no step is being missed
out yeah interesting
example
okay any questions about this
example okay
let's then see another example but
within the same heading so it's still
part of example number six in
contrast let's consider two again taus
nodes or the surface noes tube noes like
this you remember this picture before
from before it's probably still on the
black there
and and this standard taus
sorry okay let's call this k0 let's call
this K1 and
let's say that these are excuse me
inside
R3 which is also inside R4 you can also
regard it as inside our R5 also inside
R6 and what have you
okay now in what dimension are they
isotopic to each other well first remark
is that those two
surfaces if you forget about moving they
are already homeomorphic in other words
they are topologically the
same one to one correspondence bje if
you know that kind of word which is
continuous in both directions they're
homeomorphic it's just that they're
positioned differently inside R3 just
the way you put it is different but
there as shapes the word is
intrinsically they are the same so
they're
homomorphic but if you try to isotope
one to the other if you try to move
deform deform them inside some ambient
space they are not
isotopic R M for M = 3 4 5 for in those
Dimensions you cannot deform one to the
other if you try to do so you run into
self intersection and according to our
definition the isotopy should have no
self
intersection in the course of the
deformation you should not cheat
however
example
um four
shows that they do become
isotopic in R six and
above okay so you have to be careful
about the concept of
isotopy naively intuitively it just
means continuous deformation but you
have to say in what ambient space you
are deforming if there isn't very much
space if you're in a small space like a
physical space r three you cannot
isotope many things
but if you go to a high if you are
inside a higher Dimension space so that
there are extra Dimensions into which we
can escape then you can isotope much
more
easily okay so in
general this is a very
very um easy statement so I'm not going
to discuss it too much Z 7 I think it's
Z 7 isn't it so if two things are
isotopic then those two things are
homeomorphic all we are saying is that
if we manage to deform one object to
another object they must be
topologically the
same but the converse the other way
around is not
true even if they are topologically the
same for example here and here
yeah you may not be able to deform one
to the
other is you may not be able to isotope
one to the other even if they are
homeomorphic whether you succeeding
isotop or not has to do with how much
ambient space you have how much ambient
Dimension you have
okay good so the
comers excuse me but this is false
[Applause]
homeomorphism does not imply
isotopic so the comment is that to
know um
which sub
manifolds are isotopic to which ones
[Applause]
it is necessary in fact it is
indispensable do you know what this word
means indispensable and disons in Fr the
same word you cannot omit this step you
have to have this yeah it's
indispensible to
specify in
what ambient
[Applause]
manifold we are trying to is
suppose bless
you that is to say often um we hear
beginners students and so on say oh this
is isotopic to this but that's not the
way to say it you say this is isotopic
this in this space because if you change
the ambient space you may no longer be
isotopic you may no longer have enough
room okay so you have to specify in what
surrounding ambient manifold you are
doing the is isoto in contrast
homomorphism when you say something's
homeomorphic to another thing you don't
have to specify anything else so we say
this might be a slightly
philosophical statement but please uh
try to
pass the sentence
homeomorphism
is an
intrinsic property if you don't know
this word you should look it up in a
dictionary it's a very useful word
yeah
whereas
isotopy is an extrinsic
property again a useful word useful
concept you should
dictionary
okay and as I kept saying it's useful to
write down the usual pattern if you have
a large ambient
space or the small ambient space how
easy or difficult it is the isotope gets
affected the larger or the smaller the
ambient space
ambient
[Applause]
mindfold or ambient Dimension let's
say
[Music]
the
easier or
harder it becomes
isotope have you noticed that there are
several words here
we started talking about isotopic that's
an adjective and then isotopy that's the
noun now we have to isotope that's a
verb and mathematicians like to you know
make everything into a verb we sometimes
even try to verb nouns